A Guide to the Galt Family Papers, 1847-1941
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg
Galt Family Papers, 1847-1875, 1847-1941.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 78.3
ca. 50 items.
Galt Family.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1978.
Alternative Form
Also available on microfilm (M-1585)
Biographical/Historical Information
Dr. John Minson Galt (1819-1862) served as the superintendant of Eastern State Hospital in Williamsburg, Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
Miscellaneous papers relating to the Galt family, especially Dr. John Minson Galt II (1819-1862), superintendent of Eastern State Hospital in Williamsburg, Va., and his sister, Sarah Maria Galt (1822-1880). Includes personal letters, architectural notes and rough sketches, newspaper clippings, genealogical information, and other miscellany. Contains information on Eastern State Hospital; attitudes toward the mentally ill; Williamsburg, Va., and its inhabitants; the disruptions of the Civil War; the Galt family; and the sculptor Alexander Galt.
Arrangement
Chronological.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Galt Family
Persons:
Galt, Alexander, 1827-1863.; Galt, John M. (John Minson), 1819- 1862.; Galt, Sara Maria, 1822-1880.
Subjects:
Architecture--Designs and plans.; Mentally ill--Care.; Sculptors-- Virginia.; Women--Virginia--Williamsburg--Social conditions--19th century.
Corporate Names:
Eastern State Hospital (Va.)
Geographical Names:
Williamsburg (Va.)--History-- Civil War, 1861-1865.
Contents List
- Drawing of Egyptian Mummy and Dr. Warren's account of the same, n.d.
- General Laws of Motion, n.d.
- List of items sent to the Eastern State Asylum by Sally M. [Sarah Maria] Galt. re: marble bust and pictures, n.d.
- Memo. Definitions, n.d.
- Memo. Notes on David, n.d.
- Richmond Medical Journal. Obituary of John M. Galt, M.D. n.d.
- Letter to Alice re Lissie's illness, Carter Randolph mentioned, n.d.
- Letter. Chatham, L[ucy] B. Saunders to Sally re Saunders's return to "old home" in Williamsburg. Family news n.d.
- Letter. Williamsburg, G. Grimes to Dr. John M. Galt re good work of Eastern Asylum and Dr. Galt in caring for those afflicted with insanity, 29 January 1847.
- Letter. Anne Arundel Co., MD. Mary McCeobe to Cousin Sally re family news, fear of childbearing, business disruptions of war, irregularity of mails to Williamsburg, 6 July 1865.
- Letter. Charlestown, [West] Virginia, Margaret M. Raum to Miss Galt re condition of her sister, a patient in the Asylum. Family news, 24 September 1865.
- Reprint: P.G. Hamlin M.D. "Dr. John Minson Galt and the Williamsburg Asylum." Virginia Medical Monthly, 68, pp. 502-50, September 1941.
- Architectural notes and sketches re plans for a new asylum? 18 items, n.d.
- Galt Family genealogical information for 1769-1836 from the Galt Family Bible. 5 items, n.d.
- Miscellany from the Galt Family Bible. 6 items and other fragments, n.d.
- Newspaper clippings. 9 items. Includes: Courier-Journal, August 23. 1875, "Virginia's First Capital. Some Historical Reminiscences of Williamsburg..." Also references to Alexander Galt, sculptor 1875.